<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the causes moouing the Queene of England to giue aide to the defence of the people afflicted and oppressed in the lowe countries</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13194</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836525</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176466</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240953580</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 9189.5</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S100695</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99836525e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 220:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the causes moouing the Queene of England to giue aide to the defence of the people afflicted and oppressed in the lowe countries</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20, 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1585]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated at end: Richmount the first of October, 1585.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A.j.".</note>
                  <note>"An addition to the declaration: touching the slaunders published of her Maiestie" has separate pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>B and C outer formes are reimposed from STC 9189.</note>
                  <note>In this edition A3r line 11 of text ends "GOD"; B2r line 7 ends "compassi-".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 9188 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Chicago. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176466:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176466:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:176466:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176466:2"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE CAVSES MOOVING THE QVEENE OF ENGLAND to giue aide to the Defence of the People afflicted and oppressed in the lowe Countries.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device, or a decoration? (not found in McKerrow)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Christopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176466:3"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176466:3"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF THE CAVSES MOVING THE QVEENE OF ENGLAND to giue aide to the Defence of the People afflicted and oppressed in the lowe Countries.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough Kinges and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Soueraignes,
<note place="margin">Kinges and Princes Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, are to yeeld account of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons onely to almighty God, the King of Kings.</note> ovving their homage and seruice onely vnto the Almightie God the king of al kings, are in that respect not bounde to yeeld account or render the reasons of their actions to any others but to God their only Soueraigne Lorde: and that amongst the most ancient and Christian Monarches the same Lorde GOD hath committed to vs the Soueraignetie of this Realme of <hi>Englande</hi> and other our dominions, vvhich vvee holde immediatly of the same Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Lord, and so thereby accountable onely to his diuine Maiestie: yet vve are notvvithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this our prerogatiue at this time specially mooued, for diuers reasons hereafter briefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, to publish not onely to our ovvne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall louing Subiectes, but also to all others our neighbours, specially to such Princes and States as are our Confederates, or haue for their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes cause of commerce vvith our Countreis and people, vvhat our intention is at this time,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176466:4"/>and vpon what iust and reasonable groundes we are mooued to giue aid to our next Neighbours the naturall people of the lowe Countries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by long warres and persecutions of strange Nations there, lamentablie afflicted, and in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent danger to bee brought into a perpetuall ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitude.</p>
            <p>First it is to be vnderstoode (which percase is not perfectly knowen to a great nomber of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons) that there hath beene,
<note place="margin">Naturall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual traffique betwixt the people of England and them of the lowe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> time out of minde, euen by the natural situation of those low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis and our Realme of Englande, one directly opposite to the other, and by reason of the ready crossing of the Seas, and multitude of large and commodious Hauēs respectiuely on both sides, a continuall traffique and commerce betwixt the people of Englande, and the Naturall people of these lovve Countries, and so continued in all ancient times when the seueral Prouinces there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as <hi>Flanders, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> and other Countries to them adioyning, were ruled and possessed by seuerall Lordes, and not vnited to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as of late yeeres they haue beene by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termariages,
<note place="margin">Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Kings of England and Lordes of the low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and also the subiects of both Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> and at length by concurrences of many and sundrie titles haue also beene reduced to be vnder the gouernment of their Lordes that succeeded to the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by there hath beene in former ages many speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all alliances and confederations, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tvvixt the Kinges of England our Progenitours and the Lordes of the said countries of <hi>Flanders,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176466:4"/>Holland, Zeland,</hi> and their adherentes: but also be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the very naturall subiectes of both Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as the Prelates, Noblemen, Citizens, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gesses, and other Comminalties of the great Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and porte Townes of either countrie reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proquelie by speciall Obligations and Stipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnder their Seales interchangeablie,
<note place="margin">The people of both the Countries bound by spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeablie, for mutuall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours &amp; friëd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offices.</note> for maintenāce both of commerce and entercourse of Marchantes, and also of speciall mutuall ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to bee obserued betwixt the people and inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of both parties as well Ecclesiasticall as Secular: and very expresse prouision in such Treaties conteined for mutuall fauours, affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all other friendly offices to bee vsed and prosecuted by the people of the one Nation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the other. By which mutuall Bondes, there hath continued perpetuall vnions of the peoples heartes together, and so by way of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall entercourses, from age to age the same mutuall loue hath bene inuiolablie kept and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercised, as it had bene by the worke of nature, and neuer vtterly dissolued, nor yet for any long time discontinued, howsoeuer the kinges, and the Lordes of the countries sometimes (though very rarely) haue bene at difference by sinister meanes of some other Princes their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, enuying the felicitie of these two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
            <p>And for maintenance and testimonie of these natural vnions of the peoples of these kingdoms and countries in perpetuall amitie, there are
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176466:5"/>extant sundrie autentique Treaties and Transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for mutuall commerce,
<note place="margin">Treaties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of anciēt time, betwixt the Kinges of England and the Dukes of Burgundie, for the commerce betwixt their Countries.</note> entercourse and straight amitie of ancient times: as for example, some very solemnely accorded in the times of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the sixth our progenitour, and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> the second Duke of <hi>Burgundie,</hi> and inheritour to the Countie of <hi>Flanders</hi> by the Ladie <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret</hi> his Grandmother, which was aboue one hundred and fortie yeeres past, and the same al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so renewed by the noble Duke <hi>Charles</hi> his sonne, Father to the King of <hi>Spaynes</hi> Grandmother, and husbād to the Ladie <hi>Margaret</hi> sister to our great Grandfather King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth: and after that, of newe oftentimes renewed by our most Noble and sage Grandfather King <hi>Henrie</hi> the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, and the Archduke <hi>Philip</hi> Grandfather to the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> now being: and in later times, often renewed betwixt our Father of Noble memorie King <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight, and <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth Emperour of <hi>Almaigne,</hi> Father also to the present King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which Treaties,
<note place="margin">Conuentions for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> subiectes of either side, to shewe mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall fauours one to the other.</note> Transactions, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations of amitie and mutuall commerce, it was also at all times specially and principally contained in expresse wordes, by conuentions, concordes and conclusions, that the naturall people and subiects of either side, should shewe mutuall fauours and dueties one to the other, and should safely, freely and securely commerce together in euery their countries, &amp; so hath the same mutuall and naturall concourse and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176466:5"/>bene vvithout interruption continued in many ages, farre aboue the like example of any other coūtries in Christendome, to the honour and strength of the Princes, and to the singular great benefite and enriching of their people, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till of late yeeres that the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of his lovve countries into <hi>Spayne,</hi> hath beene (as it is to be thought) counselled by his counsellers of <hi>Spayne,</hi> to appoynt <hi>Spaniardes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Spanyards and strangers lately appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted gouerners in the lowe Countries, to the violation of the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Countrie.</note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reners and strangers of strange blood, men more exercised in vvarres then in peaceable gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; some of thē notably delighted in blood, as hath appeared by their actions, to be the chiefest gouernours of all his sayde lovve coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, contrary to the ancient lavves &amp; customes thereof, hauing great plentie of noble, valiant and faithfull persons naturally borne, and such as the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> and the King himselfe had to their great honours vsed in their seruice, able to haue bene employed in the rule of those countries. But these <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> being meere strangers, hauing no naturall regarde in their gouernement to the maintenance of those coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and people in their ancient and natural ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of peaceable liuing, as the most noble and vvise Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> yea, &amp; as his sonne king <hi>Philip</hi> himselfe had, vvhilest he remained in those countries, and vsed the counsels of the States &amp; natural of the coūtries, not violating the ancient liberties of the coūtries: but contraryvvise, these <hi>Spaniardes</hi> being exalted to absolute gouernmēt, by ambition, and for priuate lucre haue violētly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176466:6"/>broken the ancient lawes and liberties of all the countries,
<note place="margin">The destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and the people of the Countries by the Spanish gouetnment.</note> and in a tyrannous sort haue banished, killed and destroyed without order of lawe within the space of a fewe monethes, many of the most ancient and principall persons of the naturall nobilitie that were most worthie of gouernement. And howe so euer in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of these cruell persecutions, the pretence thereof was for maintenance of the Romish re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, yet they spared not to depriue very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Catholiques and Ecclesiasticall persons of their franchises and priuiledges: and of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest that were executed of the Nobilitie, none was in the whole countrie more affected to that religion then was the noble and valiant Countie of <hi>Egmond,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble violent death of the Countie of Egmond, the glory of those Countries.</note> the very glorie of that countrie, who neither for his singular victories in the seruice of the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> can be forgotten in the true histories, nor yet for the crueltie vsed for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, to bee but for euer lamented in the heartes of the naturall people of that countrie. And furthermore, to bring these whole countries in seruitude to <hi>Spaine,</hi> these forreine gouernours haue by long intestine warre, with multitude of <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> and with some fewe <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains,</hi> made the greater part of the said countries (which with their riches by common estimation, answered the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> equally to his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias</hi>) in a maner desolate, and haue also lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly destroyed by sworde,
<note place="margin">The riche townes and strengthes with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wealth thereof posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by the Spaniardes.</note> famine, and other cruell maners of death, a great part of the naturall peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and nowe the rich townes and strong places
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176466:6"/>being desolate of their naturall inhabitants, are held &amp; kept chiefly with force by the <hi>Spanyardes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which pitifull miseries and horrible cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of these most rich countries and people, are of all their neighboures at this day, euen of such as in auncient tyme haue bene at frequent discord with them, thorowe naturall compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very greatly pitied, which appeared speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally this present yeere, when the <hi>Frenche</hi> king pretended to haue receiued them to his protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, had not (as the States of the countrey and their deputies were answered) that certayne vntimely and vnlooked for complottes of the house of <hi>Guyse,</hi> stirred and maintained by money out of <hi>Spayne,</hi> disturbed the good and generall peace of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and thereby vrged the king to forbeare from the resolution hee had made, not onely to ayde the oppressed people of the lowe countries against the <hi>Spanyardes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The French kings offers to haue aided &amp; receiued to his subiection the oppressed people of the lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> but also to haue accepted them as his owne subiectes. But in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie trueth, howsoeuer they were pitied, and in a sort for a tyme comforted and kept in hope in <hi>Fraunce</hi> by the <hi>Frenche</hi> king, who also hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentymes earnestly solicited vs as Queene of <hi>Englande,</hi> both by message and writing to bee carefull of their defence: yet in respect that they were otherwise more straightly knitte in auncient friendship to this realme then to any other countrie, wee are sure that they could bee pitied of none for this long tyme with more cause and griefe generally, then of our subiects
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176466:7"/>of this our realme of <hi>England,</hi> being their most ancient allies and familiar neighbours, and that in such maner, as this our realme of <hi>England</hi> and those countries haue bene by cōmon language of long time resembled and termed as man and vvife.
<note place="margin">The Queene of Englandes continuall frendly adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the king of Spaine for restraining of the tyrannie of his gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</note> And for these vrgent causes and many others, vve haue by many friendly messages and Ambassadours, by many letters and vvritings to the said king of <hi>Spayne</hi> our brother and allie, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared our compassion of this so euill and cruel vsage of his naturall and loyall people by sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie his martiall gouernoures and other his men of warre, all strāgers to these his countries. And furthermore, as a good louing sister to him, and a natural good neighbour to his lowe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and people, wee haue often, and often a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine most friendly warned him, that if hee did not otherwise by his wisedome and princely cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie restraine the tyranny of his gouernours and crueltie of his men of warre, wee feared that the people of his countries shoulde bee forced for safetie of their liues, and for continuance of their natiue countrie in their former state of their liberties, to seeke the protection of some other forreyne Lord, or rather to yeelde them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues wholy to the soueraigntie of some migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Prince, as by the ancient lawes of their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and by speciall priuiledges graunted by some of the Lordes and Dukes of the countries to the people, they doe pretend and affirme, that in such cases of general iniustice, and vpon such
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176466:7"/>violent breaking of their priuiledges they are free from their former homages, and at libertie to make choise of any other prince to bee their prince &amp; Head. The proofe whereof, by exāples past is to be seene &amp; read in the ancient histories of diuers alterations, of the lordes and ladies of the countries of <hi>Brabant, Flanders, Holland,</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> and other countries to them vnited by the States &amp; people of the countries, and that by some such alterations, as the stories doe testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, <hi>Philip</hi> the Duke of <hi>Burgundy</hi> came to his tytle, from which the king of <hi>Spaynes</hi> interest is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but the further discussion hereof, we leaue to the viewe of the monuments and recordes of the countries.
<note place="margin">The Queene of Englandes meanes vsed to staie the States of the lowe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries from yeelding their subiection to any other forreine Prince.</note> And now for the purposes to stay them from yeelding themselues in any like sort to the soueraigntie of any other strange Prince, certaine yeeres past, vpon the earnest request of sundrie of the greatest persons of degree in those countries, and most obedient subiects to the King, such as were the Duke of <hi>Ascot,</hi> and the Marques of <hi>Hauery</hi> yet liuing, and of such others as had principall offices in those countreis in the time of the Emperour <hi>Charles,</hi> wee yeelded at their importunate requests, to graunt them prests of money, onely to continue them as his subiects, and to maintaine themselues in their iust defence against the violence and cruelties of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> their oppressours, thereby staying them from yeelding their subiectiō to any other Prince frō the said king of <hi>Spayne:</hi> and during the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176466:8"/>time of that our aide giuen to them, and their stay in their obedience to the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> wee did freely acquainte the same king with our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and did still continue our friendly aduices to him, to moue him to commaund his gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and men of warre, not to vse such insolent cruelties against his people, as might make them to despayre of his fauours, and seeke some other Lorde.</p>
            <p>And in these kinde of perswasions and actions wee continued many yeeres, not onely for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion of the miserable state of the countries, but of a naturall disposition to haue the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient conditions of straight amitie and cōmerce for our kingdomes and people to continue with the States &amp; the people of the saide Dukedome of <hi>Burgundie</hi> and the appendants, and namely with our next neyghbours the countries of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland.</hi> For wee did manifestly see, if the nation of <hi>Spayne</hi> shoulde make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of those countries, as was and yet is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly intended, and plant themselues there as they haue done in <hi>Naples</hi> and other countries, adding thereto the late examples of the violent hostile enterprise of a power of <hi>Spanyardes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prise of the Spaniardes in Ireland sent by the king of Spayne and the Pope.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sent within these fewe yeeres by the king of <hi>Spayne</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> into our Realme of <hi>Ireland,</hi> with an intent manifestly confessed by the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that those nombers were sent aforehand to sease vpon some strength there, to the intent with other greater forces to pursue a conquest
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:176466:8"/>thereof: wee did we say againe, manifestly see in what danger our selfe, our countries and people might shortly bee, if in conuenient time wee did not speedily otherwise regard to preuent or stay the same. And yet notwithstanding our sayde often requests and aduises giuen to the King of <hi>Spayne,</hi> manifestly for his owne weale &amp; honour, wee founde him by his counsell of <hi>Spayne</hi> so vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing in any sort to encline to our friendly counsell, that his gouernours and chiefetaines in his lowe countries increased their cruelties towardes his owne afflicted people, and his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in <hi>Spayne</hi> offered dayly greater iniuries to ours, resorting thither for traffique: yea,
<note place="margin">The refusall of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Queenes messenger, and her let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the King of Spayne.</note> they of his counsell in <hi>Spayne,</hi> woulde not permit our expresse messenger with our letters to come to the King their masters presence: a matter very strange, and against the lawe of nations.</p>
            <p>And the cause of this our writing and sending to the King,
<note place="margin">The iust cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of dismis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardin Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doza out of England.</note> proceeded of matter that was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be knowen to the King, and not vnmeete nowe also to be declared to the worlde, to shewe both our good disposition towardes the King in imparting to him our grieues, and to let it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare howe euill we haue beene vsed by his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, as in some part may appeare by this that followeth. Although wee coulde not haue these many yeeres past any of our seruaunts whome we sent at sundrie times as our Ambassadours to the King our good brother as was meete, suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to continue there without many iniuries and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176466:9"/>indignities offered to their families, and diuers times to their owne persons by the greatest of his Counsellours, so as they were constrained to leaue their places, and some expelled and in a sort banished the Countrey, without cause gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by them, or notified to vs: yet we, minding to continue very good friendship with the king, as his good Sister, did of long time and many yeeres giue fauourable allowance to all that came as his Ambassadours to vs, sauing onely vpon manifest daungerous practises attempted by two of them to trouble our estate, whereof the one was <hi>Girald Despes,</hi> a very turbulent spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted person, and altogether vnskilfull &amp; vnapt to deale in Princes affaires being in amitie, as at his retourne into <hi>Spayne</hi> hee was so there also repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The other and last was <hi>Bernardin de Mendoza,</hi> one whome we did accept and vse with great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour a long time, as was manifestly seene in our Court, and we thinke cannot be denied by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, but yet of late yeeres (we know not by what direction) we found him to be a secret great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourer to sundrie our euill disposed and sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous subiectes, not onely to such as lurked in our Realme, but also to such as fled the same being notoriously condemned as open Rebelles and Traitours, with whome by his letters, messages and secret counsels hee did in the ende deuise howe with a power of men, partly to come out of <hi>Spayne,</hi> partly out of the low Countries, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee gaue them great comfort in the Kinges
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:176466:9"/>name, an inuasion might bee made into our Realme, setting downe in writing the manner howe the same should be done, with what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men and shippes, and vpon what coastes, portes &amp; places of our Realme by special name, and who the persons should be in our Realme of no small account, that should fauour this Inuasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and take part with the Inuadours, with many other circumstances declaring his full set pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and labours taken, to trouble vs and our Realme very dangerously, as hath beene most clearely proued and cōfessed by such as were in that confederacie with him, whereof some are fled &amp; now do frequent his companie in <hi>France,</hi> and some were taken, who confessed at great length by writing the whole course herein helde by the saide Ambassadour, as was manifestly of late time published to the worlde vppon <hi>Francis Throgmortons</hi> a principall Traitours examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And when we found manifestly this Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadour so dangerous an instrument, or rather a Head to a rebellion and Inuasion, and that for a yeere or more together hee neuer brought to vs any letter from the King his Master, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing our often request made to him that hee woulde by some letter from the King to vs, let it appeare that it was the Kings will that he should deale with vs in his Masters name in sundrie thinges that he propounded to vs as his Ambas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sadour, vvhich vvee did iudge to be contrary to the Kinge his Masters vvill: vvee did finally
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176466:10"/>cause him to be charged w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> these dāgerous practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, &amp; made it patēt to him how, &amp; by whō, with many other circūstances we knew it, &amp; therfore caused him in very gētle sort to be cōtent within some resonable time to depart out of our realme, the rather for his own safety, as one in very deed mortally hated of our people: for the which, we graūted him fauorable cōduct,
<note place="margin">Barnardin Mendoza fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the Realme.</note> both to the sea &amp; ouer the sea: &amp; thereupon we did speedily send a seruāt of ours into <hi>Spaine</hi> w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> our letters to the king, only to certify him of this accidēt, &amp; to make the whole matter apparant vnto him: &amp; this was the messēger afore mēcioned, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> might not be suffred to deliuer our message or our letters to the king.</p>
            <p>And beside these indignities, it is most manifest how his ministers also haue both heretofore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times, &amp; now lately practised here in <hi>England</hi> by meanes of certaine rebelles, to haue procured sundry inuasions of our Realme, by their forces out of <hi>Spayne</hi> &amp; the low Countries: very hard re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cōpences (we may say) for so many our good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. Hereupō we hope no reasonable person cā blame vs, if we haue disposed our selues to chāge this our former course, &amp; more carefully to look to the safety of our selfe &amp; our people: &amp; finding our owne dāgers in deed very great &amp; imminēt, we haue bene the more vrgently prouoked to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt &amp; accelerate some good remedy, for that besides many other aduices giuē vs both at home and frō abrode, in due time to withstād these dā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, we haue found the general disposition of al our own faithful people very ready in this case, &amp;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176466:10"/>earnest in offring to vs both in Parliaments &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise, their seruices w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> their bodies &amp; blood, &amp; their aides with their lands &amp; goods, to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand &amp; preuent this present common danger to our Realme &amp; thēselues, euidently seene &amp; fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the subuerting &amp; rooting vp of the anciēt natiō of these low coūtries, &amp; by plāting the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> nation &amp; men of warre, enemies to our coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, there so nere vnto vs. And besides these oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions &amp; cōsiderations, we did also cal to our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrāce our former fortunate proceeding by Gods special fauor, in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> beginning of our reigne,
<note place="margin">The Queene of Englandes proceeding for the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from the seruitude wherein the House of Guyse meant to haue brought it.</note> in remedying of a like mischief that was intēded against vs in <hi>Scotlād</hi> by certaine <hi>French</hi> men, who then were directed only by the house of <hi>Guise,</hi> by colour of the mariage of their Neece the Queene of <hi>Scots</hi> with the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of <hi>Frāce,</hi> in like maner as the ofsprings of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> said house haue euē now lately sought to attaine to the like vnordinate power in <hi>France:</hi> a matter of some cōsequēce for our selues to cōsider, although we hope the king our good brother professing sincere frendship towards vs, as we professe the like to him, will moderate this aspiring greatnes of that house, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> neither him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe nor y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Princes of his bloud be ouerruled, nor wee (minding to cōtinue perfect frendship with the king &amp; his bloud) be by the said house of <hi>Guise</hi> and their faction disquieted or disturbed in our Countries. But nowe to returne to this like ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Scotlande</hi> aforesaide, when the <hi>French</hi> had in like maner (as the <hi>Spanyardes</hi> haue nowe of long time attempted in the lowe Countries)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176466:11"/>sought by force to haue subdued the people there, and brought them into a seruitude to the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> and also by the ambitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires of the saide house of <hi>Guise,</hi> to haue procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to a warre by vvay of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest of our crowne for their Neece the Queene of <hi>Scottes</hi> (a matter most manifest to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon knovvledge of the vvorlde:) it pleased Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, as it remaineth in good memorie to our honour and comfort, to further our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and honourable and iust actions at that time in such sort, as by our aiding then of the nation of <hi>Scotland</hi> being sore oppressed with the <hi>French,</hi> and vniuersally requiring our aide, wee procured to that Realme (though to our great cost) a full deliuerance of the force of strangers and danger of feruitude, &amp; restored peace to the whole Countrie, which hath continued there euer since many yeeres, sauing that at some time of parcialities of certaine of the Noble men, as hath beene vsuall in that Countrie, in the myno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the yong King there hath risen some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles,
<note place="margin">The Realme of Scotlande restored to the ancient free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and so possessed by the present King by the meanes onely of the Queene of England.</note> which for the most part we haue in fauour of the King and his Gouernours vsed meanes to pacifie: so as at this day such is the quietnes in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as the King our deare brother and cousin, by name, <hi>Iames</hi> the sixth, a Prince of great hope for many good Princely respectes, raigneth there in honour and loue of his people, and in very good and perfect amitie with vs and our Countrie. And so our actions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176466:11"/>at that time came to so good successe by the goodnes of God, as both our owne Realme, and that of <hi>Scotland,</hi> hath euer since remained in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amitie and peace then can bee remembred these manie hundred yeeres before, and yet no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing heereby done by vs, nor any cause iustly giuen, but that also the <hi>French</hi> kinges that haue since succeeded, which haue bene three in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and all brethren, haue made and concluded diuers treaties for good peace with vs, which presently continue in force on both parties, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding our foresaide actions attempted for remoouing out of <hi>Scotland</hi> of the saide <hi>French</hi> forces, so transported by the onely direction of the house of <hi>Guyse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore,
<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of the causes of sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of english souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of the oppressed people of the low countries, and to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Realme.</note> to conclude for the declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our present intention at this time, wee hope it shall of all persons abroad be well inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted, as wee knowe it will be of such as are not ledde by parciallitie, that vpon the often &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall lamentable requests made to vs by the vniuersall States of the countries of <hi>Holland, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Guelders</hi> &amp; other prouinces with them vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (beeing desperate of the king of <hi>Spaynes</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours) for our succours to bee yeelded to them, onely for their defence against the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and other strangers, and therewith finding manifest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by our often and importunate requests and aduices giuen to the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> no hope of reliefe of these their miseries, but rather an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease therof by dayly cōquests of their townes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176466:12"/>and slaughter of their people, (though in very trueth wee cannot impute the increase of any late cruelties to the person of him that now hath the tytle of generall gouernour, shewing his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall disposition more inclynable to mercie and clemencie, then it seemeth hee can direct the heartes of the <hi>Spaniardes</hi> vnder him, that haue bene so long trayned in shedding of blood vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the former <hi>Spanish</hi> gouernors:) And ioyning thereunto our owne dāger at hand, by the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw &amp; destructiō of our neighbours, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse &amp; planting of the great forces of the <hi>Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> so neere to our coūtries, with precedēt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of many troublesome attemptes against our Realme: we did therfore by good aduice and after long deliberation determine, to sende cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine companies of souldiers to ayde the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall people of those countries,
<note place="margin">English power sent onely to defende.</note> onely to defende them and their townes from sacking and desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thereby to procure them safetie, to the honour of God, whome they desire to serue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely as christian people according to his holy word, and to enioye their ancient liberties for them and their posteritie, and so consequently to preserue and contynue the lawful and ancient commerce betwixt our people and those coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries and ours.</p>
            <p>And so, we hope our intention herein, &amp; our subsequent actions will be by Gods fauour both honorably and charitably interpreted of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons (sauing of the oppressors thēselues, &amp; their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176466:12"/>partizans) in that wee meane not heereby, either for ambition or malice, (the two rootes of al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iustice) to make any particular profit hereof to our selfe or to our people,
<note place="margin">
                  <p>Three special things reason<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably desired by the Queene of England.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ende of wars with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutiō of the low Countries to their anciēt liberties.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Suretie from inuasiō of her owne Realme.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. And renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Traffique betweene the Countries.</p>
               </note> onely desiring at this time to obtaine by Gods fauour for the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, A deliuerāce of thē from warre by the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niardes</hi> and Forraines, with a restitution of their ancient liberties &amp; gouernement by some chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian peace, And thereby, a suretie for our selues and our realme to be free from inuading neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, And our people to enioyin those coūtries their lawful commerce &amp; entercourse of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship &amp; marchandise, according to the ancient vsage and treaties of entercourse, made betwixt our Progenitors and the Lordes and Earles of those countries, and betwixt our people and the people of those countries.</p>
            <p>And though our further intentiō also is or may be to take into our garde,
<note place="margin">The causes of taking some Townes into her Maiesties custodie.</note> some fewe townes vpō the sea side next opposite to our realme, which otherwise might be in danger to be taken by the strāgers, enemies of the coūtry: yet therein consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering we haue no meaning at this tyme to take and retaine the same to our owne proper vse, we hope that al persons wil thinke it agreeable with good reason &amp; princely policie, that we should haue the gard &amp; vse of some such places for sure accesse &amp; recesse of our people &amp; soldiers in safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; for furniture of them with victuals &amp; other things requisite and necessary, whilest it shall be needful for them to cōtinue in those coūtries for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:176466:13"/>the aiding therof in these their great calamities, miseries, and imminent daunger, and vntill the countries may be deliuered of such strāge forces as do now oppresse them, and recouer their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lawfull liberties and maner of gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to liue in peace as they haue heeretofore done, and doe nowe most earnestly in lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner desire to doe, which are the very onely true endes of all our actions nowe inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, howsoeuer malitious tongues may vtter their cankred conceits to the contrary, as at this day the worlde aboundeth with such blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous reportes in writings and infamous libels, as in no age the Deuill hath more abounded with notable spirites replenished with all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednesse to vtter his rage against professours of Christian Religion. But thereof we leaue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge to God the searcher of hearts, hoping that he beholding the sinceritie of our heart, wil graunt good successe to our intentions, whereby a Christian peace may ensue to his diuine honour, and comfort to al them that loue peace truely, and wil seeke it sincerely.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="addition">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176466:13"/>
            <head>AN ADDITION TO THE DECLARATION: TOVCHING THE SLAVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders published of her Maiestie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter we had finished our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, there came to our hands a Pamphlet written in <hi>Italian,</hi> printed at <hi>Milan,</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Nuouo aduiso,</hi> directed to the Archbishop of <hi>Milan,</hi> conteyning a report of the expugnation of <hi>Anwerpe</hi> by the Prince of <hi>Parma:</hi> by the which we found our selfe most maliciously charged with two notable crimes, no lesse hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the worlde, then most repugnant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our owne naturall inclination. The one, with ingratitude towards the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who (as the authour saith) saued our life being iustly by sentence adiudged to death in our sisters time: The other, that there were some persons procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be corrupted with great promises, and that with our intelligence as the reporter addeth in a parenthesis in these wordes <hi>(as it was said)</hi> that the life of the Prince of Parma should be taken away: and for the better proouing and countenancing of this horrible lie, it is further added in the saide
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176466:14"/>Pamphlet, that it pleased the Lorde God to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer this, and bring two of the wicked persons to iustice. Now, knowing howe men are malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously bent in this declining age of the world, both to iudge, speake and write maliciously, falsly and vnreuerently of Princes: and holding nothing so deare vnto vs, as the conseruation of our reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and honour to be blamelesse: we found it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie expedient, not to suffer two such horrible im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations to passe vnder silence, least for lacke of answere, it might argue a kinde of guiltinesse, and did therefore thinke, that what might be alledged by vs for our iustification in that behalfe, might most aptly be ioyned vnto this former Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion nowe to be published, to lay open before the worlde the maner and ground of our proceeding in the causes of the lowe Countreyes.</p>
            <p>And for answere of the first point wherewith wee are charged touching our ingratitude to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> as we do most willingly acknowledge that we were beholding vnto him in the time of our late sister, which we then did acknowledge very thankefully, and haue sought many wayes since in like sort to requite, as in our former Declaration by our actions may appeare: so doe wee vtterly denie as a most manifest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trueth, that euer he was the cause of the sauing of our life as a person by course of Iustice sentenced vnto death, who euer carried our selfe towardes our said sister in duetifull sort, as our loyaltie was neuer called in question, much lesse any sentence
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:176466:14"/>of death pronounced against vs: a matter such, as in respect of the ordinarie course of proceeding, as by processe in Lawe, by place of triall, by the Iudge that should pronounce such sentence, and other necessary circumstances in like cases vsuall, especially against one of our qualitie, as it coulde not but haue bene publiquely knowen, if any such thing had bene put in execution. This then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, wee leaue to the worlde to iudge howe maliciously and iniuriously the authour of the saide Pamphlet dealeth with vs, in charging vs by so notable an vntrueth with a vice that of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers we doe most hate and abhorre. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the manifest vntrueth of this imputation, men not transported with passion may easely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne what vntrueth is conteined in the second, by the which wee are charged to haue bene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with an intended attempt against the life of the said Prince: a matter if any such thing should haue bene by vs intended, must haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded either of a mislyking wee had of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or that the prosecution of the warres in the lowe Countreyes was so committed vnto him, as no other might prosecute the same but he.</p>
            <p>And first for his person, we could neuer learne that he hath at any time, by acte or speache, done any thing that might iustly breede a mislike in vs towards him, much lesse a hatred against his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in so high a degree, as to bee either priuie or assenting to the taking away of his life: Besides, he is one of whom we haue euer had an honourable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176466:15"/>conceite, in respect of those singular rare partes we alwaies haue noted in him, which hath wonne vnto him as great reputation, as any man this day liuing carrieth of his degree and qualitie: and so haue we alwayes deliuered out by speache vnto the world, when any occasion hath bene offered to make mention of him. Nowe, touching the prosecution committed vnto him of the warres in the lowe Countreys, as all men of iudgement knowe that the taking away of his life carrieth no likelyhood that the same shall worke any ende of the said prosecution: so is it manifestly knowen, that no man hath dealt more honourablie then the saide Prince, either in duely obseruing of his promise, or extending grace and mercie where merite and deserte hath craued the same: and therefore no greater impietie by any coulde bee wrought, nor nothing more preiudiciall to our selfe, (so long as the King shall continue the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of the cause in that forcible sort he now doeth) then to be an instrument to take him away from thence by such violent meanes, that hath dealt in a more honourable and gracious sort in the charge committed vnto him, then any other that hath euer gone before him, or is likely to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede after him.</p>
            <p>Nowe therefore how vnlikely it is, that we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither cause to mislike of his person, nor that the prosecution of the warres shoulde cease by losse of him, should be either authour, or any way assenting to so horrible a fact, wee referre to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176466:15"/>the iudgement of such as looke into causes, nor with the eyes of their affection, but doe measure and weigh things according to honour and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. Besides, it is likely if it had bene true that we had bene any way chargeable, (as the author re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth) the confessions of the parties executed, (importing such matter, as by him is alledged) would haue bene both produced and published: for malice leaueth nothing vnsearched, that may nourish the venime of that humour.</p>
            <p>The best course therefore that both we and all other Princes can holde in this vnfortunate age that ouerfloweth with nombers of malignant spirits, is through the grace and goodnesse of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, to direct our course in such sort, as they may rather shewe their willes through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, then with iust cause by desert, to say ill, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face Princes either by speach or writing: assuring our selues, that besides the punishment that such wicked and infamous libellours shall receiue at the handes of the Almightie for deprauing of Princes and lawfull Magistrates who are Gods ministers, they both are and alwayes shall be thought by all good men, vnworthie to liue vpon the face of the earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Richmount <date>the first of October, 1585. and the 27. yeere of the reigne of our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lady the Queene,</date> to be published.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>